<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<chapter id="Administration_Console_User_Guide-Navigation_Panel">
	<title>Navigation Panel</title>
	<para>All applications and resources discovered during server start up
		should be available underneath the JBoss Application Server instance in the navigation tree. The
		example below demonstrates a view with items in the tree expanded.</para>
	
	<mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="images/Expanded.png"/>
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	
	<note>
		<para>
			The navigation panel is currently fixed width so to see wider entries use the scroll bar at the bottom of the panel.
		</para>
	</note>
	
	<para>The are two sorts of items shown in the navigation panel:</para>
	
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>Collection of resources: These items are indicated by a yellow
				folder icon.</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>Individual resources: These are indicated by a blue document
				icon.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata depth="152"
				   fileref="images/Resource_Nav.jpg"
				   width="326" />
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	
	<para>Clicking on a collection resource (for example, the
		<emphasis>Resources</emphasis> link above) will render in the main panel
		either:</para>
	
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>a list of resource categories from where you can drill down
				further:</para>
			
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="images/Resource_Panel.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para>or a list of actual resources from where you can drill down to see
				a particular resource. For some resource types you can create or delete
				instances of a resource from this view.</para>
			
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="images/Admin-Console-QuickStart_html_ma5a1ef5.jpg"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<para>Expanding one of the folder nodes in the navigation will show either
		individual resources or further collections of resources which themselves
		can be expanded.</para>
	
	<para>Click on an individual resource will show the Summary tab for that
		resource, as seen previously for the JBoss Application Server instance. If available, expanding
		an individual resource node in the navigation will show the child resources
  it has deployed within it.</para>
</chapter>

